Cambodia Subject Files, Inclusive: 1970-2003, Bulk: 1974-1991
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Cambodia Subject Files
Inclusive: 1970-2003, Bulk: 1974-1991
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
7
Keston Institute, 1969 -
2 A4 document boxes
The Cambodia Subject Files contain a variety of materials pertaining to Cambodian refugees, the country’s international relations, foreign aid, religion, and religious persecution.
Administrative Information
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the name changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist and totalitarian countries. The Keston Archive and Library houses numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
Keston collected documents dating between 1970 and 2003 reflecting the political and religious climate of Cambodia.
After gaining independence from France in 1953, the Kingdom of Cambodia was established under King Sihanouk. Two years later Sihanouk stepped down, allowing his father to become king while he remained the head of the government. After his father’s death in 1960, Sihanouk became head of state but did not return to the throne.
During the Vietnam War, North Vietnamese and Vietcong troops used eastern Cambodia to launch attacks into South Vietnam. Discontent with the North Vietnamese settlement in Cambodia and the Communist guerrilla movements, the Khmer Rouge began pressuring the government in Phnom Penh to take action. In 1970, while Sihanouk was abroad, General Lon Nol led a coup that overthrew the government. Lon Nol installed himself as president of the Khmer Republic, also called the State of Cambodia, and sent the army to fight the North Vietnamese. Cambodia reached a peace agreement in 1973 that called for the withdrawal of foreign forces. However, the fighting continued.
Lon Nol’s rule was short lived. In 1975 (Year Zero), the Khmer Rouge led by Pol Pot occupied the Cambodian capital city of Phnom Penh. Sihanouk was briefly reinstated as head of state and renamed the country Kampuchea. Shortly thereafter, Khieu Samphan replaced him, and Pol Pot became prime minister. Renaming the country Democratic Kampuchea, Pol Pot and the Khmer Rouge remained in power until 1979.
Under the Khmer Rouge, city dwellers were forcibly moved to the country in an attempt to transform Cambodia into a Marxist agrarian society. With the move, money became worthless, and basic freedoms were curtailed, including freedom of religion. Those who showed signs of education were frequently tortured or executed, and ultimately hundreds of thousands of the educated middle-class were exterminated. Consequently, most of Cambodia’s professional and technical classes disappeared. Disease, starvation, and exhaustion killed many more. An estimated 1.7 million deaths occurred during Pol Pot’s regime.
While Cambodia was ruled by Pol Pot and the Khmer Rouge, fighting broke out between Vietnam and Cambodia. In January 1979, Vietnam seized Phnom Penh. Pol Pot and the Khmer Rouge fled to the border with Thailand. The Vietnamese established the People’s Republic of Kampuchea, and the country attempted to return to life before the Khmer Rouge. However, during the Vietnam backed government control, hundreds of thousands of people became refugees as guerrilla warfare tore across Cambodia.
Even when the pro-Vietnamese Kampuchean People’s Revolutionary Party won the 1981 parliamentary elections, the international community refused to recognize the new government. The United Nations continued to recognize the exiled Khmer Rouge and Sihanouk as the rightful authority. Hanoi-backed Hun Sen became prime minister in 1985. By 1989, an agreement between the warring factions was reached, and Vietnamese troops began withdrawal. Hun Sen abandoned socialism to attract foreign investors. The country was renamed the State of Cambodia, and Buddhism was reinstalled as the state religion.
With the signing of the 1991 Paris Peace Accords, parties vying for control agreed to share power temporarily, and Sihanouk again became head of state. In the 1993 general election, the royalist political party, FUNCINPEC (Front uni national pour un Cambodge indépendant, neutre, pacifique et coopératif), won the majority of the seats, followed by Hun Sen’s Cambodian People’s Party. A multi-party coalition was formed with FUNCINPEC’s Prince Norodom Ranariddh as prime minister and Hun Sen as deputy prime minister. Sihanouk returned to the post of king, and the name returned to the Kingdom of Cambodia. The 1993 election ended the Khmer Rouge’s representation in the United Nations.
In 1994, thousands of Khmer Rouge guerrillas surrendered with assurance of government amnesty. King Sihanouk granted amnesty to Ieng Sary, the deputy leader of the Khmer Rouge who formed a new party. In 1997, Hun Sen mounted a coup against Prime Minister Ranariddh. That same year, the Khmer Rouge put Pol Pot on trial and sentenced him to life imprisonment where he died in April 1998. July 1998 also saw another round of elections as Hun Sen became prime minister and Prince Ranariddh became the president of the National Assembly.
With the turn of the millennium, Cambodia enacted a law allowing charges to be brought against Khmer Rouge leaders. Trials continued for many years, and in 2016, a United Nations-backed tribunal upheld the convictions and life sentences of Nuon Chea and Khieu Samphan, holding them responsible for murder and crimes against humanity in the deaths of perhaps as many as 2.2 million Cambodians.
Scope and Content
Cambodia subject files consist of newspaper clippings, bibliographic references, news reports, and background briefs.
The materials cover the period from 1970-2003 with the bulk from 1974-1991. The majority of the materials pertain to Cambodian refugees, international relations and aid, and religion.
Materials regarding Cambodian refugees concentrate on refugee camps along the border of Thailand and accounts of atrocities committed by the Khmer Rouge. Items pertaining to international relations focus heavily on relations between Cambodia, Vietnam, China and Thailand. Smaller holdings include Australia, Indonesia, the United Kingdom, the United States, and the Soviet Union. These materials also document the call for international aid. Religious materials center most prominently on Buddhism and Roman Catholicism. Other documents note religious revival, conversions, and oppressive practices relating to religious activity.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the Cambodia materials organized simply into Cambodia General Files. Within the category, materials were arranged by broad subjects. This organization has mostly been preserved but has been divided into specific thematic subjects.
The Cambodia Subject Files are arranged in one series: I. General
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 7.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Pol Pot.
Subjects (Organizations)
Catholic Church -- Cambodia.; Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.; Parti communiste du Kampuchea.; Party of Democratic Kampuchea.
Places
Cambodia -- Foreign relations.; Cambodia -- History -- 1975-1979.; Cambodia -- History -- 1979-; Cambodia -- History -- Civil War, 1970-1975.; Cambodia -- Politics and government -- 1979-; Cambodia -- Religion.
Subjects
Buddhism -- Cambodia.; Cambodia -- Politics and government -- 1975-1979.; Cambodian-Vietnamese Conflict, 1977-1991.; Civil rights and socialism -- Cambodia.; Communism -- Cambodia.; Decommunization -- Cambodia.; Freedom of religion -- Cambodia.; Genocide -- Cambodia.; International relief -- Cambodia.; Persecution -- Cambodia.; Political atrocities -- Cambodia.; Refugee camps -- Cambodia.; Refugees -- Cambodia.; Religion and state -- Cambodia.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.)
- General, 1970-2003; 1
  Administrative Information
  Scope and Content
  General Cambodia subject files contain information on the history of the country, Pol Pot, the government, international relations, emigration, communism, human rights, and religion.
  - General, 1974-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Individuals: Pol Pot, 1982-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Khmer Rouge, 1978-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Khmer Rouge Military Actions, 1979-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Individuals: Prince Sihanouk and the Anti-Vietnamese Coalition, 1975-1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Government, 1974-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Elections, 1981-1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Refugees, 1975-1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Constitution, 1976-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Church and State, 1977-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Basic Rights and Freedoms, 1978-1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Law, 1995-2001 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Prisons and Labor Camps, 1979-1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Oppressive Practices, Physical Assault, and Murder, 1975-1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Trials, 1979-2003 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - International Relations: Australia, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - International Relations: China, 1975-1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - International Relations: Indonesia, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - International Relations: Soviet Union, 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - International Relations: Thailand, 1977-1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - International Relations: United Kingdom, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - International Relations: United States of America, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - International Relations: Vietnam, 1977-1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - International Relations: Vietnam, 1986-1999 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Western Reactions, Interventions, Protests, and Criticism, 1977-1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Humanitarian Aid, 1977-1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Contacts with International Organizations, Conferences, and Peace Organizations, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Contacts with International Organizations, Conferences, and Peace Organizations, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - United Nations and United Nation Specialized Agencies, 1977-1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Amnesty International, 1977-1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Visits To and From Other Countries, 1977-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Religion: General, 1970-1999 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Chhirc Taing, 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bibles, 1975-1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Conversions, 1977-1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Oppressive Practices Relating to Religious Activity, 1972-1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Buddhism, 1970-2002 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Islam, 1974-1987 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Roman Catholicism, 1975-1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Religious Revival, 1975-1999 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Religious Statistics, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Communism: General, 1975-1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Ideological and Religious Broadcasts from the West, 1975-1999 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Economy, 1975-1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Health, 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Tourism, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Culture, 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Literature, 1978-198 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Film: The Killing Fields, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Monuments of Cultural Heritage: Angkor Wat, 1978-1999 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Youth, Children, 1980-1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)